Guide to the Thomas M. Disch Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas M. Disch papers
1908-2006
1950-2006
YCAL MSS 851
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
92.17
(113 boxes) + 1 art
Disch, Thomas M., 1940-2008
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: June 1991 Acquisition, October 1994 Acquisition, January 2000 Acquisition, September 2006 Acquisition.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 24-25, 43, and 110-113 (electronic files and computer): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 44-45 and 108-109 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas M. Disch, 1991-2000. Purchased from James Cummins on the Sinclair Lewis Fund, 2006.
Thomas M. Disch (1940-2008)
Thomas Michael Disch, American speculative fiction author and poet. Disch was the author of novels, poetry, playscripts, opera libretti, literary criticism, and Amnesia, a video game. Among his best-known novels are Camp Concentration (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1968), 334 (Boston: Gregg Press, 1972), On wings of song (New York: St. Martin's Press, 1979), and The Brave Little Toaster goes to Mars (New York: Doubleday, 1986).
Disch was born in Des Moines, Iowa, on Feb. 2, 1940, and committed suicide in 2008 in New York City. His partner of over 30 years, Charles Naylor, predeceased him in 2005.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the personal and professional life of American speculative fiction author and poet Thomas M. Disch. Evidence of Disch's creative process, relationships with contemporary authors, and wide-ranging writing style is found in the writings, which include autograph manuscript and typescript drafts and corrected proofs of Disch's novels, short stories, libretti, and poetry. Among the correspondents represented in the collection are Brian Aldiss, Philip K. Dick, and Michael Moorcock. The collection consists of diverse media and, in addition to audiovisual material, photographs, electronic files, and an art object, includes documentation of the development of Amnesia, a video game authored by Disch. The collection's chief research interests are its documentation of speculative fiction, science fiction, twentieth-century American poetry, and dystopian literature.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Dystopias in literature; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Science fiction -- 20th Century; Speculative fiction, American -- 20th Century; Video games -- Authorship; Audiovisual material -- United States -- 20th Century; Born digital -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; LGBTQ resource; Aldiss, Brian W. (Brian Wilson), 1925-2017; Dick, Philip K., 1928-1982; Disch, Thomas M., 1940-2008; Moorcock, Michael, 1939-
- June 1991 Acquisition, 1956-1991; 23.04; (25 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three series: I. Writings. II. Correspondence. III. Other Papers.
  - Writings, Series I
    Arranged alphabetically, chiefly by title.
    - "A," poem, typescript, undated (Box 1)
    - "ABCDEFG HIJKLM NOPQRST UVWXYZ," poetry collection, typescript, with related correspondence, 1978, undated
    - "A la recherche de Marilyn Hacker," essay, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Affluence of Edwin Lollard," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Affluence of Edwin Lollard," short story, published clipping, undated
    - "After the April Festivals," poem, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Afterwards," afterword, typescript, undated
    - "Against Beauty," poem, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Alex Katz Paints 'The Wedding,'" essay, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "An American Camera in Outer Space," commentary on photography exhibit, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The American Flag," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - Amnesia (video game)
      - Plot outline and notes, typescript, with autograph notes, undated
      - Plot flowchart, typescript, photocopy, undated
      - Notebook, autograph manuscript, undated
      - Screenplay fragment, typescript, undated
      - Computer printouts, original, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Computer printouts, photocopy, undated
      - Game covers for the Apple II, 3 copies, 1985; 3
      - Game cover for the Commodore 64, 1985
      - Cover art and press release, 1985
      - Cover art and text, 1985; 2
      - Game typescript, 1985; 4
      - Game typescript, 1985; 3
      - Outline, typescript, 1985; 2
      - Outline, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1985
      - Marketing descriptions, typescript, with cover letter, typescript, unsigned, 1985
      - Notes, autograph manuscript and typescript, 1985
      - Program listing, computer printout, with autograph note, 1985
      - Program listing, computer printout, 1985; 2
      - Program listing, computer printout, 1985; 3
      - Final program listing, computer printout, with manuscript note from "Don", 1985; 2 (Box 2)
      - Final program listing, computer printout, 1985; 2
      - Step outline, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1985
      - Game maps, photocopy, 1985
      - Notes and fragments, typescript, 1985
      - Scoring system, manuscript notes, photocopied, 1985
      - Notes and correspondence, typescript, 1985
      - Related correspondence, 1985
      - Game reviews, clippings, and photocopies, 1986-1987
      - Review and publicity information, typescript, 1987
      - Related magazines, 1986-1987
      - Information about Electronic Arts, typescript, 1985
      - Computer media
        Conditions Governing Access
        Boxes 24-25 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
        - Game for IBM and Apple II computers, 1985; 5; 10 electronic disks
          Box 24: Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
          - AMNESIA Disk side one of two (c) 1985, Cognetics All rights reserved, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0001; 1 (Box 24)
          - Amnesia 5.8 SIDE B KE 4.38 3/7/85, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0002; 1 (Box 24)
          - AMNESIA By Thomas M. Disch and Cognetics Corporation Disk 1 (Boot this side), 1991-ycal-0606-c-0003; 1 (Box 24)
          - AMNESIA By Thomas M. Disch and Cognetics Corporation Disk 2, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0004; 1 (Box 24)
          - AMNESIA 1, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0005; 1 (Box 24)
          - AMNESIA 2, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0006; 1 (Box 24)
          - AMNESIA by Thomas M. Disch and Cognetics Corp. Disk 1, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0007; 1 (Box 24)
          - AMNESIA by Thomas M. Disch and Cognetics Corp. Disk 2, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0008; 1 (Box 24)
        - Game for the Commodore 64 and 128 computers (12 copies), 1985; 12; 24 electronic disks
          Box 25: Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
          - AMNESIA by Thomas M. Disch and Cognetics Corp. Disk 1, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0009; 1 (Box 25)
          - AMNESIA by Thomas M. Disch and Cognetics Corp. Disk 2, 1991-ycal-0606-c-0010; 1 (Box 25)
    - "An All-Day Poem," typescript, with autograph corrections, undated (Box 3)
    - "The Angel," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Angouleme," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Another Letter to W.C.2," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Anticipation," poem, typescript, 4 copies, 1 signed, undated
    - "Apartment Next to the War," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Argument Resumed," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Arts Poetica," poem, typescript, photocopy, undated
    - "The Asian Shore," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "Assassin and Son," short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Assassination of the Mayor," poem, typescript, undated
    - Assorted poems, typescript with autograph notes, undated
    - Assorted short stories, payment records, undated
    - "At the Van Gogh Museum," poem, typescript, 1985 October 24
    - "Atocha Choo-Choo," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Attila on Fifth Avenue," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Audition" (play)
      - Typescript, photocopy, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Typescript, with cover letter, 1983 March 14
    - "Auntie and the Pirates," essay, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Aus der Tiefe rufe ich," poem, typescript, undated
    - Autobiography
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections and accompanying letters, 1985-1986
      - Typescript, corrected, and proofs, 1986 April
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Back Here," poem, typescript, undated
    - Bad Moon Rising (anthology)
      - Proposal for an anthology, typescript, carbon, undated
      - Introduction and table of contents, typescript, carbon, undated
      - Reviews by various authors, typescript, photocopies and clippings, 1973
      - Contracts and financial records, 1972-1979; 2
    - "The Baron, Danielle, and Paul," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1964 January
    - "The Beard," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Ben Hur," play, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Biggest Group in the World," short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Birds," short story, published clipping, undated
    - Black Alice (novel)
      - Foundry proofs, 1968; 2
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Chapter 1, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Review by Sanders, clipping, 1968
    - "The Black Cat," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "A Black Christmas," portion and outline, typescript, with manuscript corrections and cover letter, 1970
    - "The Black Lotus," outline, typescript, with manuscript corrections, undated
    - "The Blindman's Sign," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Bodies," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Bombadiers," poem, typescript, 6 copies, undated
    - "Bon-Bons," short stories index, typescript, undated
    - "Bone of Contention," short story, typescript, carbon, undated
    - "Box 514," poetry collection, typescript, carbon, undated
    - The Brave Little Toaster Goes to Mars (novel)
      - Typescripts, undated; 2
      - Contract, undated
      - Typescripts, undated; 3
    - "A Brief Elegy," poem, typescript, undated (Box 4)
    - "Brig A Zoon," short story, typescript, with manuscript corrections, undated
    - "Brotherhood and Good Will Resolve An Insoluble Situation," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections and attached notes, undated
    - "A Bunch of Things," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Burn This," poetry, typescripts, undated; 2
    - "The Business of Burying People," poem, typescript, undated
    - The Businessman (novel)
      - Proofs, bound, 1984; 4
      - Outline for novel, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Typescript, undated; 3
    - Camp Concentration (novel)
      - Source materials for fugue, typescript and autograph manuscript with newspaper clipping, undated
      - Synopsis, typescripts, with autograph corrections, 1969, undated; 3
      - Proofs, with manuscript corrections, 1969; 2
      - Contracts and financial records, 1970-1971
    - "Canned Goods," short story, typescript, 2 copies, 1 with autograph corrections, undated
    - "CAPS grant application"
      - Poem, typescript, undated
      - Materials, 1981-1983; 2
    - "The Cardinal Detoxes," a one-act play, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Carrousel," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Casablanca," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, and published clipping, undated
    - "Causes and Effects," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Celebrity Love," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Champs of Paradise," poetry collection, typescript, undated
    - "China," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Chthonian Smell," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The City of Penetrating Light," short story, published clipping, undated
    - "The Civilians," poem, typescript, 2 copies, 1 with autograph corrections, undated
    - Clara Reeve (novel)
      - Proof, with manuscript notes, 1975 (Box 5)
      - Typescripts with autograph corrections, undated; 2
      - Fragment, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Draft fragments, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - First draft, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Book One [with Book Two frontispiece], typescripts, with manuscript corrections, undated; 2
      - Book Two, typescripts, with autograph corrections, undated; 3
      - Typescripts, undated; 2
    - "The Clever Prince," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Close Your Eyes Now"
      - Short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Clouds," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Coal Miners," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Collaborators," short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Colors," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "Come, Pleasant Death," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "Come to Venus Melancholy" (short story)
      - Typescript, and published clipping, undated
      - Financial records, 1987
    - "Coming to the Mountain," poem, typescript, with autograph notes, 2 copies and a computer printout, undated
    - "Concepts" (novella)
      - Typescript, with letter from Harlan Ellison, undated
      - Typescript, undated
    - "Concerning the Recent Victories," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Constellations," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Contest," short story, typescript, and published clipping, undated
    - "Convalescing in London," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Corporate Guerrilla," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Cosmology and Us," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Cow," poem, typescript, undated
    - "A Cow of Our Time," essay, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "A Cow of Our Time," poetry collection, typescript, undated
    - "Cramming by Cassette," article, typescript, with related correspondence, 1987 (Box 6)
    - "The Crumbling Infrastructure," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Cubist Paintings of Lesser Museums," poem, typescript, 1982 October 5
    - "The Customer," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Dan De Lion"
      - "Dan De Lion" and "Waking on New Year's Day," first drafts, notebook, undated
      - Poem, typescript, 1984
      - Poem, typescript, undated
      - "The Tale of Dan De Lion", 1986
    - "Dangerous Flags," short story, typescript, 1969
    - "Danny's New Friends From Deneb," short story, published clipping, undated
    - "The Day Euterpe Died," poem, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Dear Mr. Bly," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Death of the Pretty Vampire," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Decaying Swan," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Defense Mechanism," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Delaunay's La Tour Eiffel," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Deluge," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Demi-Urge," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Descending," short story, typescript, and published clipping, 1963 November
    - "The Descent of the West End," short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Desert of Vast Eternity" and "There is an Index by First Lines," poems, submitted to Amazing, typescript, with manuscript notes, 1983
    - "The Deterrent," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, and a page of autograph notes, 1981 March 24
    - "Diamant Noir," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Discovery of the Nullitron" (short story)
      - Published clipping, undated
      - Typescript, undated
    - "Displaying the Flag," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Donna Anna Writes to Her Sister," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, with 4 pages of autograph notes, undated
    - "Doomsday Machine," collected column stories, typescript, with relevant correspondence, 1974, undated
    - "The Double-Timer," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1962 June
    - "Doubting Thomas," short story, typescript, 1965
    - "Downtown," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Echo and Narcissus," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Echo of Wrath," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Echo Round His Bones," financial records, 1970
    - "Eclogue," dramatic script, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "An Ecomium Celebrating Alexander," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Embarrassment of Science Fiction" (article)
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Typescript, undated
    - "The Empty Room," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Energy Crisis in Perspective," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Eric," poem fragment, autograph manuscript, undated
    - "Et in Arcadia Ego," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Eternity," novel fragment, typescript, 3 copies, with autograph notes, undated
    - "Europe," poem, typescripts, 3 copies, undated
    - "Europe: The Lost Continent" (article)
      - Proposal, typescript, undated
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "Events of the Day," poem, typescript, 1976 August 5
    - "Everyday Life in the Later Roman Empire," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Everything Closes After Midnight: A London Lament," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Feathers from the Wings of an Angel," short story, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "February 22, 1970," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Fetishist's Lament," poem, typescript, undated
    - "A Few of My Favorite Things," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1976 August 4
    - "Final Audit" (short story)
      - Autograph manuscript, with water damage, undated
      - Published clipping, with water damage, undated
    - "The Fire Began to Burn the Stick, the Stick Began to Beat the Dog," short story, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Flight Useless, Inexorable the Pursuit," short story, typescript and photostat, and published clipping, undated
    - "The Floating Panzer," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Foetus" (short story)
      - Typescript, with manuscript notes and accompanying letter, 1980 July 30
      - Contract, 1979 November
    - "Fool's Mote," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "For a Derelict," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Forbidden Thought," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "Four Crosswords, of Graded Difficulty," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Four Poems from Stories," poems, typescript, undated
    - "Frankenstein" (playscript)
      - Fragments, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Fragments, autograph manuscript, undated
      - Fragments, typescript and manuscript, undated
      - Partial script, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Notebook, autograph manuscript, undated
      - Libretto, typescript and autograph manuscript fragments, undated
      - Libretto, typescript, 1981
    - "The Freedom Years of Mrs," script, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "A Friendly Dialogue," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Full Circle: An Introduction to Ringtime," autograph corrections, undated
    - "Fun With Your New HEAD," short story, typescript, and published clipping, undated
    - "Fun With Your New Head," collected short stories, proofs, 1968
    - "A Game of Armageddon," novel fragment, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Genetic Coda," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Genre Subjects," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "A German Drinking Song," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Getting in Touch With My Mom," short story, photostat, 2 copies, undated
    - "Getting Into Death," short story, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Getting Into Death," cover for short story collection, undated
    - "The Ghost Who Had It," short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Girl With the Vita-Gel Hair," short story, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Glandier," novel fragment, typescript, undated
    - "Glandier's Wife," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Going Down, Being There, and Coming Back," article, typescript, undated
    - "The Goldberg Variations," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Good Forms," fragment, manuscript, undated
    - "Grand Central Terminal," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Grand Tour," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Great Dropouts," article, typescript, undated
    - "The Grown-Up," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Guerrilla," short story, typescript, photostat, undated
    - "Guggenheim Application," poem, typescript, with autograph notes, 2 copies, undated
    - "Guile Evicted," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Harp That Conquered Hell," short story, typescript, photostat, 2 copies, 1964, undated (Box 7)
    - "The Harvest Is Past, the Summer Is Ended," novel, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated; 2
    - "Hell Revisited," interview with Kingsley Amis, typescript, undated
    - "Her First Ball," short story, autograph manuscript, undated
    - "Here I Am, There You Are, Where Were We?" collected poems, typescript, proofs, circa 1982
    - "High Purpose In Poetry: A Primer," poem, typescript, undated
    - "His Own Kind," short story, typescript, undated
    - "History as Weather," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The House of Morden," proposal for a novel, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "How to Behave When Dead," poem, typescript, undated
    - "How to Fly," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "I Remember John," essay, typescript, undated
    - "The Idolator," poem, typescript, undated
    - "If You Don't Frug, Baby, What Do You Do?," short story, typescript, undated
    - "In a Time of Plague," poem, typescript, undated
    - "In Memoriam, Nal Einmal," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1982
    - "In Our Lifetime," commercial presentation, typescript, 2 drafts of outline, and OCEAN sample presentation, 1981 September
    - "In Praise of Older Women," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "In Stolid Jersey," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Incredible Giant Hot Dog," short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Incredible Shrinking Corpse," script, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "An Inspirationed Verse," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated